Welcome to the
second part of the
pharmacology of
diuretic agents.
There are three in this
group, the last three
that we'll talk about.
Thiazides, potassium sparing
diuretics, and there
are two in this class,
and osmotic diuretics.
Dr. Goldstein speaking.
Please contact me if you'd like
to chat about pharmacology.
Learning Objectives,
the same ones in Part
1 because this is
actually just one lecture.
And Preparation Materials,
if you wish to use them.
And the Key Points about
these three groups in Part 2.
And the Thiazide Diuretics.
these act in the distal
convoluted tubule
they block the NCC
the sodium chloride
co-transporter and
there are two really
structural categories here
the original thiazides which
are now called the thiazide
type they have this
benzothiazine ring and
hydrochlorothiazide is a prototype
here you see the sulfonamide
moiety again and chlorothiazide
the chlorothiazide what
you the main claim to
fame with it is it's IV
the others are not and the
thiazide like these came
along a little bit later they
have a slightly different
structure but the same actions
and chlorothaladone is the
prototype in this one and
it's an important drug
clinical trials have been
studied using this drug and
hydrochlorothiazide too but
chlorothaladone we'll talk
about now i put some board
relevant drug specific
features down here about and
endapamide and metalazone uh
i'm not asking you to remember
these by name but they
are important and you can
look at why they're important
on your own if you wish.
Pharmacokinetic
takeaways with these
drugs. I put some
arrows here to help you.
Well-absorbed, bioavailability
generally good, moderate
protein binding. What are
we thinking about with that?
Okay, well, protein binding,
it's going to have to
be taken up by OAT secretion.
But some of it's going to
get through by glomerular
filtration, the free drug.
They're not metabolized.
And they are excreted
as intact drugs in their
half-lives series. So
the half-lives really
is the difference
between these two drugs.
hydrochlorothiazide has
a fairly short half-life
and an action of anywhere
between 6 and 12 hours
chlorthaladone on the
other hand has a longer
half-life and a very
long duration of action
so how does that matter the
longer duration of action
means that it's going to
provide smoother 24-hour
blood pressure control so
it's on board for a longer
period of time the blood
levels remain stable for a
longer period of time but
also as you would expect I
think there's a higher risk
of hypokalemia than with
hydrochlorosiazide
and that's basically
what you need to remember
about these drugs.
NCC inhibition,
looking at the left-hand side.
Here's our NCC and we're
going to be blocking this
so sodium and chloride
are going to be excreted.
Since
Since only about 5% to 10
% of filtered sodium gets
down to this portion of
the nephron and can be
blocked by the thiazide
diuretics, it's going to have
moderate natriuretic and
diuretic efficacy. see.
Looking now to the
right-hand side, we're
going to be talking
about calcium
reabsorption, local
calcium export mechanism.
So here's calcium.
This is, if it's
in the lumen, it's
filtered calcium.
So by blocking sodium,
by blocking this channel,
that's going to lower
the intracellular sodium.
And therefore,
sodium is going to
come through here.
That's going to enhance
basolateral NCX1 activity.
Sodium in. And at the
same time calcium goes
out. So that's going to
pull calcium from the
lumen through this TRPV
channel and out into the
interstitial space and
into the bloodstream.
This has a minor effect.
It's just a fine-tuner.
so sodium i mean sorry
blocking ncc increasing the
five to ten percent of
filtered sodium that passes
through there will in turn
lower sodium intracellular
sodium concentrations pulling
sodium in, calcium out,
and calcium into
the cell from the
lumen, and then out
into the bloodstream.
This is a review of
the urine electrolyte
effects of all of these drugs.
Thiazides are here, so
you have a comparison,
and also lute plus
thiazide is here.
So we see really
increase in the amount of
natriuresis and diuresis
with the combination
and also increase in
sodium wasting effect.
Let's see, what else do
I want to talk about?
It can cause magnesium
loss, and that's
because of some
internal mechanisms that
reduce magnesium
uptake from the lumen.
And I want to highlight
this box right here.
Thiazide diuretics
impair the kidney's
ability to excrete
dilute urine,
remembering that the
thick ascending limb and
the distal convoluted
tubule are the diluting
segments because they're
impermeable to water.
So by blocking sodium
reabsorption from those
segments, it stays in the
lumen. So the lumen fluid
has an increase in solute
concentration, and that's
going to impair excretion
of free water. At the
same time, thiazides do
not impair the ability of
the kidneys to concentrate
urine because they
have nothing to do with
the medullary gradient,
unlike the loop diarism.
And that can lead to
hyponatremia, and I'll explain
that mechanism in a bit.
Now looking at this one.
Thiazide can produce
hyperglycemia and insulin
resistance, along with mild
dyslipidemia, and they can
increase lithium levels, and
I'll talk about that soon.
These are all mechanisms
you should know.
Okay, let's talk about
hypertension first, because
thiazide is the first line.
These are guideline-directed
first-line drugs for the
management of hypertension.
They can be given alone.
They're frequently
given along with another
antihypertensive agent.
Their initial effect is
to lower blood pressure
by decreasing extracellular
fluid volume. Of
course, you expect that.
And by decreasing plasma
volume, that's going
to decrease cardiac
output and that's going
to lower blood pressure.
The sustained effect,
however, with chronic use
is due to the chronic
depletion of sodium in vascular
smooth muscle. And
that's going to decrease
responsiveness to
vasoconstrictors. So, over time,
the body readjusts to a
new steady state of sodium
in, sodium out, and it
produces this reduced
responsiveness of
vascular smooth muscle to
vasoconstrictors, and
that's going to provide this
persistent peripheral
vascular resistance reduction.
Hydrochlorosiazide is the
most widely used, even
though it's not as long
-acting as chlorothaladone.
And it's present
largely because it's
present in many
fixed combination
products with
antihypertensive agents.
Chlorothaladone has a
much longer half-life,
but it's not in as many
combination products.
so one you might say okay
smoother longer lasting
blood pressure reduction
must be better well we need
studies in order to find
that out and there have
been large-scale observational
studies and randomized
clinical trials that have
shown that both drugs
reduce blood pressure and
decrease the risk of heart
attack, stroke, and heart
failure at similar rates.
And that's really
the end result.
That's what we're
looking for, a reduction
in cardiovascular
adverse events.
But chlorothaladone might be
better tolerated
by some people.
It's an individual specific
thing. You'll know your
patient, you'll know what
the best approach is.
thiazide diuretic can be
used in edema also and
usually for sequential
nephron blockade with a loop
diuretic so nkcc2 ncc
both of these get blocked
sequential and sequential
blockade and synergy okay
vasopressin resistance
this has been known for
decades and decades as
nephrogenic diabetes insipidus.
Nomenclature is kind
of transitioning over
to vasopressin
resistance because it is
really descriptive
of what's happening.
And we're going to include
lithium-induced vasopressin
resistance. So the
treatment, I put it here,
just so you know, is a
thiazide diuretic, low-sodium
diet, low-protein diet,
so getting low solutes,
and an NSAID. Oh, do we not use
NSAIDs with thiazide
diuretics? Well,
this is a case where we need
to for the mechanistic effects.
Okay, so what is
vasopressin resistance?
That means that the
collecting duct is
not responsive to
ADH or vasopressin.
NCC blockade by thiazide
diuretics shifts sodium
reabsorption upstream.
So what we're doing
actually here is reducing
the amount of water
that's being excreted,
reducing polyuria. So how
do we give a thiazide
diuretic to reduce urine
excretion? Doesn't make
sense, does it? Well,
it's because thiazide
causes volume contraction.
Remember that?
Mild volume contraction
is going to cause RAS
activation and decrease
GFR, and then less sodium
will come in, and whatever
sodium comes in will
be reabsorbed in the
proximal tubule along with
water, and that will
cause a substantial drop
in the filtrate. In other
words, the amount of
sodium and water that's
flowing through the tubules
and reaching the ADH
-sensitive sites in the
collecting ducts. Thus,
overall urine output
decreases by up to 50%.
That reduces the overall
conservation of water. So
this is one of those peculiar
things where the
thiazides are intended to
reduce polyuria by overall
conservation of water.
And has to be done
together with low sodium
diet, low protein diet,
meaning low solutes coming
into that body, being
taken in, along with an
NSAID, which we know
will counteract the
prostaglandin effects of
sodium and water excretion.
NSAIDs are going to
enhance ADH activity.
moving down now down to
kidney stones nephrolithiasis
caused by hypercalciuria
in other words too
much calcium in the urine
well that kind of makes
sense because thiazides
are going to cause calcium
to be reabsorbed in the
distal convoluted tubule
and that might reduce the
kidney stone recurrence.
This is about recurrence
in selected patients.
And of course it's not the only
thing. Increase
fluids to keep the
increase in fluids to
hopefully dilute the calcium.
Diet, weight loss drug therapy.
Adverse effects are
going to be related to
reduction in extracellular
volume as you
could expect, hypotension,
hyponatremia. Let's
move down now to
hyponatremia mechanism.
Okay,
to repeat,
NCC block impairs urine
dilution because it's
preventing the solutes from
being reabsorbed so they stay
in the filtrate. And just
because there's so much
solute in there, free water,
in other words, solute
free water can't be
excreted to the same degree.
Now the concentrating ability
is not impaired. So the
water gets reabsorbed. And
what happens is more water
gets reabsorbed than
sodium. Sodium keeps being
blocked. Sodium reabsorbs
and continues to be blocked.
but the water is being
reabsorbed and then people
are often thirsty or
drink too much water along
with all of this water
being reabsorbed and that
can dilute this amount of
sodium in the bloodstream
and that will reduce sodium
concentrations
dilutional hyponatremia.
concomitant NSAID increases
the risk by enhancing
ADH effect so more
water goes in more water
gets reabsorbed please
know that mechanism
hypokalemic metabolic
alkalosis we talked about
that with the loop
diuretics it's the same
idea here hypomagnesemia
low magnesium levels
Chronic thiazide use leads
to DCT, distal convoluted
tubule remodeling,
and down regulation of
this magnesium channel,
which the name is TRPM6.
M stands for magnesium.
And that's going to
decrease magnesium
reabsorption and
increase magnesium
wasting. And that
should be monitored.
Hypercalcemia. This
is, we talked about the
mechanism of calcium being
reabsorbed, but that's really
uncommon because calcium
levels in the blood
are so tightly controlled
by parathyroid hormone.
Hyperuricemia, let's
go to that mechanism.
Hypovolemia, okay, we
get this extracellular
fluid contraction. contraction.
So uric acid levels will
go up, as you would expect.
And on top of it, thiazides
will decrease uric
acid excretion at the
level of the transporter.
So uric acid levels can
go up. Now, hyperglycemia
may not be a problem
for most people, but
for individuals who
have a tendency for a
gout attack, that can
exacerbate a gout attack.
Hyperglycemia with
insulin resistance.
Let's take a look at that one.
this is all about
hypokalemia again insulin
is released from the
beta cells of the
pancreas the endocrine
pancreas and the
insulin release is
regulated by a particular
channel, which is an
ATPase potassium channel.
So in hypokalemia,
that can cause that
channel to open and
insulin to be released.
So we get, oh no, sorry.
In hypokalemia, it
can prevent that channel
from opening and that
will impair insulin
release and therefore
that can lead to
hyperglycemia. On top of it,
thiazide diuretic
can reduce insulin
sensitivity. So we get insulin
resistance between
those two mechanisms.
And hyperlipidemia.
Well, there can be
mild alterations and
lipid metabolism that's
most likely related to
this impaired insulin
sensitivity effect.
So we're starting to see
some kind of mild metabolic
syndrome, which for most
people is not an issue,
but it can be for those
who are vulnerable to it.
And GI intolerance,
that's rare.
Pregnancy may decrease
placental perfusion.
These should not be used
unless the benefit to
the mother outweighs
the risks to the fetus.
So drug interactions,
loop diuretics,
antihypertensives, they
work well together.
NSAIDs, we talked
about this a number of
times. NSAIDs cause
afferent arterial
vasoconstriction,
lowers renal blood flow,
and GFR, and drug secretion.
That reduces delivery
of the thiazide to the
DCT. and say it's
increased sodium and water
reabsorption, blood
pressure lowering effects.
Lithium now.
Lithium takes advantage
of sodium transporters.
So enhanced sodium excretion,
we get a compensatory
reabsorption of sodium and
lithium in the proximal
tubule that increases
plasma lithium levels.
And lithium has a
narrow therapeutic
window, so lithium toxicity.
Digitalisglycosides, this is
related to the
hypokalemia again.
Antidiabetic drugs
because of the
hyperglycemic
effect of thiazides.
Probenicid because probenicid
relies on organic
anion transport.
Amphotericin B, again,
because of potassium
loss. bi-amphotericin B
as well as the thiazide
and glucocorticoids
for the same reason,
potassium loss.
And here are the
review questions
to help you know
what you need to know
and answers if you wish
to pause and see them
and more
and some more because
thiazides are really
important drugs and
do lots of things.
and more.
So I'll go over these
in a supplemental
video. Here's a
little case vignette.
And now we come to our renal
epithelial sodium
channel inhibitors.
Ameloride and triamterine.
Ameloride has the star.
It is a very important
drug, widely used.
Pharmacokinetic takeaways,
the ENAK inhibitors are orally
absorbed, moderately
protein bound.
And actually they
enter the nephron via
the OCT, the organic
cation transporter.
ameloride is not
metabolized triamptorine is
and they are really
excreted and the half
-lives as you say are
long enough to allow once
or twice daily dosing
it's a matter of effect
mechanism this is the
physiology i won't go over that
part here we have our
epithelial sodium channel so
this is what we're blocking
so that's going to decrease
sodium reabsorption that
is going to neutralize or
diminish this lumen negative
gradient so remember it
needs a lumen negative
gradient for potassium to be
secreted so that's gone so
potassium is not secreted and
it gets reabsorbed all
right I should say it can
accumulate in the blood
potassium sparing effect and this
is just a review of all of
them so you can compare.
Clinical uses.
Well,
hypertension and edema,
basically the ENAC inhibitors
are used as adjuncts
to a potassium losing,
potassium wasting drug.
So frequently used with a
thiazide diuretic for
hypertension treatment to increase
denatrieresis and diuresis,
and also to counteract
the potassium wasting
effect of the thiazide.
This is lithium again.
ENAC inhibitors to reduce
lithium-induced vasopressin
resistance in patients
who need to continue loose
lithium. So why? This is
the pathophysiology here.
Lithium-induced vasopressin
resistance occurs because
lithium will enter the
epithelial cell through the
epithelial sodium channel
and because it doesn't get
exported out the basal lateral
membrane it will therefore
accumulate inside the
epithelial cell and that
accumulation is going to cause
various effects that lead
to down-regulation of the
AQPT aquaporin channels.
And therefore, if those
AQP2 are not present,
then no matter if ADH
is present, it's not
going to cause
reabsorption of free water.
It's resistant,
vasopressin resistant.
So what do we do?
Well, if we block the
epithelial sodium
channel, that's going to
prevent the lithium
from going in, correct?
So, we're getting to the root.
Now, in addition, we talked
about this with thiazides
and vasopressin resistance.
add the thiazide to cause
this mild extracellular
fluid contraction with the
proximal sodium and water
reabsorption to reduce the
polyurea. So that's the two
together, preventing lithium
from getting inside the
epithelial cell and causing
reduction in urine volume
by the use of the thiazide
diuretic. And this is for
people, I mean, discontinuing
lithium is the best thing
to do. But some people are
stabilized on lithium. They
should be continuing on
lithium. So this is just an
opportunity to mitigate that
vasopressin resistance
that's caused by the lithium.
Little syndrome. This is
a rare condition in which
there is autosomal dominant
mutation that causes
increases in the number of
epithelial sodium channels.
And so that's going to
increase the potassium
reabsorption. So by blocking
the epithelial sodium
channels and putting
the patient on a sodium
-restricted diet will manage
the hypertension and the
hyperkalemia should be
caused by this disorder.
Let me restate that,
I'm getting myself
confused with all
of these things.
So by increasing the amount
of sodium that gets reabsorbed
through the epithelial
sodium channel, that's going
to increase secretion of
potassium because it's going
to create that lumen negative
potential, and that's
going to lead to hypokalemia.
So it's correct on here.
So by blocking the
channel, that's
going to mitigate
these problems. So
cautions now.
Now, we know that ENAC
inhibitors will cause
hyperkalemia, and so patients
who are at risk are older
patients, patients who
are on high dose, so it's
a dose-dependent effect,
high dose ENAC inhibitor
therapy. And I would
include mineralocorticoid
receptor antagonist therapy
as well, renal impairment,
people with low aldosterone
levels, and combinations
of drugs that impair
potassium excretion. So
drugs, anything that increases
the amount of potassium
in the bloodstream is
really contraindicated.
So drugs that increase
potassium in the
bloodstream, hyperkalemia,
The RAS inhibitors, ACE
inhibitors, ARBs, and
direct renin inhibitors.
NSAIDs, potassium supplements,
and calcinurin inhibitors.
Maybe you remember
cyclosporine and tacrolimus.
Which brings us to
mineralocorticoid
receptor antagonists.
Spironolactone and aplarinone.
And also finarinone,
and others will be
added, I'm sure, over as
you get to clinical
practice. You may see more.
Spironolactone
is the prototype.
It is, you see it has this
hormonal type of structure.
Oh, that's aldosterone. Here's
spironolactone. You
see the similarity.
Here's the plarinone.
Pharmacokinetic
takeaways. ways. I just
put these two on
here. Well absorbed,
highly protein bound,
hepatic metabolism,
renal and biliary excretion,
and half-life support once
or twice daily dosing.
Remembering though that
these drugs enter through
the basolateral membrane to
get to the mineralocorticoid
receptor within the
cell. It is a hormone
receptor similar to, the
action is similar to the
corticosteroid receptors,
the glucocorticoid receptors.
Aldosterone is a corticosteroid
from the adrenal cortex.
Spironolactone,
plarinone, both oral.
Let's see, what do I
want to take? Let's
look at the takeaways
here. Hepatic metabolism,
spironolactone has
active metabolites.
The active metabolites increase
spironolactone's
duration of action.
Spermolactone
itself isn't around
long. Plasma half
-life is pretty short.
Terminal half-life
is pretty short.
But canranone has a long half
-life and enteroepatic
circulation.
Eplerinone CYP3A4 does not
have active metabolites,
and its duration is
still seven to nine
hours, even though its
half-life is less than
two hours. And that's
because it acts inside
the cell on the
mineralocorticoide receptor.
And here it is.
Number of actions.
Like all hormones,
it has a lot of things it does.
This is the actions
of aldosterone.
So this is everything
we're blocking.
These drugs block the biologic
effects on the synthesis
and activation of epicellial
sodium channels, sodium
-potassium ATPases, and
other functions, leading to
excretion of sodium on water
and retention of potassium
and hydrogen, the opposite
effects of aldosterone.
The higher the patient's
aldosterone level, the
greater the effects of
the antagonists on urinary
excretion of electrolytes.
So if aldosterone is not
present, and it's not
activating the mineralocorticoid
receptor and all of
these various processes,
then the difference
and the effect of the
mineralocorticoid receptor
antagonist is going to be much
less than when the
aldosterone is highly active.
I put cortisol here because
it's on the picture.
cortisol itself activates
mineralocorticoid
receptors however where
mineralocorticoid receptors
are present there is
this enzyme 11-beta
-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase
type 2 that will
inactivate cortisol it
will shift it over to
cortisone which is the
inactive form of cortisol.
So that happens to
be present here.
So that's it.
What are we using it for?
Well, edema, this is to
combine with other diuretics
that are potassium wasting.
So it will produce the
potassium sparing effect
that will sort of blunt the
potassium wasting effect,
edema and hypertension.
Primary aldosteronism, so it's
blocking the effects
of aldosterone.
Goals of therapy to raise
serum potassium to high normal
range, normalize blood
pressure, reverse the effects
of hyperaldosteronism
on heart and kidneys. So
aldosterone works in other
places, not just in the kidneys.
Heart failure patients, both
with reduced or preserved
ejection fraction, and
this is based on studies
of spironolactone in
these patient populations.
Mineralocorticoid receptor
is overexpressed in blood
vessels and heart, and
this This overexpression
contributes to inflammation,
myocardial remodeling, fibrosis,
as well as the sodium
retention and potassium loss
that's occurring because
of aldosterone. So, it's
been found in studies that
putting spironolactone on
after the patient is stabilized
can improve outcomes.
liver cirrhosis.
Well, spironolactone
is preferred. It's the
first-line drug because
the point of it is to
block the overactive
aldosterone that's occurring
because of the liver
cirrhosis. It's occurring
because of this
excessive RAS activation.
It can be used with furosemide,
but furosemide is
not used alone.
And spironolactone has
anti-androgenic effects,
so it's used for the
treatment of acne, for
hirsutism in females, and
also in transgender women.
Adverse effects and
cautions, hyperkalemia.
Spironolactone causes these
gynecomastia impotence
loss of libido feminizing
effects because
it is an androgen
receptor antagonist and it
also interferes with
testosterone biosynthesis.
And that shifts the estradiol
-testosterone balance
towards estradiol.
Eplerinone and
finarenone do not
have this androgen
antagonist effect.
So drug interactions,
anything that
increases potassium
levels, interestingly,
spironolactone can cause
false results on serum
digoxin levels, eplerinone,
CYP3A4, so we have to
remember that and that
includes grapefruit juice.
And that brings us to our
review questions and these
are answers if you wish
to pause the computer and
more questions and more.
I'm covering both epithelial
sodium channels and
mineralocorticoid receptor
antagonists. And here's a
little tiny case vignette.
And finally, our
osmotic diuretics.
Only mannitol is on this list.
Urea, glycerin, and
isosorbiter here.
Mannitol is this very
simple structure,
simple, it's this little sugar.
I'm bringing your
attention to these SGLT2
inhibitors. These are
for diabetes, chronic
kidney disease, heart
failure. It's got, it's
really increasing its
numbers of indications.
It was designed to,
for diabetes treatment,
type 2 diabetes,
because it blocks
glucose reabsorption
in the proximal tubule,
increases urinary
excretion of glucose.
And therefore, with all
of this extra solute,
it becomes like an osmotic
diuretic. And that's
the reason I put it
here. But I'm not going
to ask you any questions
on it. It's just
sort of to raise your
awareness of the SGLT2
inhibitors, which you
will be learning about.
Okay, osmotic diuretics. Well,
they're pharmacologically
inert. They don't have any
action of their own. They
are distributed only in
extracellular fluid. They do
increase the osmotic
pressure in the extracellular
fluid. They are freely filtered
through the glomerulus.
So you need a
functioning kidney.
They are not reabsorbed
by the nephron.
mannitol lasts around
its half-life is around
five hours so it's
in for quite a while
onset of diuresis in
one to three hours so if
it's injected first of
all it needs to be by
bolus injections not
continuous infusion and
you're not going to see
a result immediately
it's going to take a little
bit of time it's used
for the management of
intracranial pressure
so start to see a
reduction maybe in half an
hour or so duration of
reduction one and a half
to six hours depending
on dosing mannitol is
not absorbed from the GI
tract so it's given IV
to any great extent. It's
a little bit absorbed.
This is a little scheme
here to show you how
these are inducing
water secretion in the
nephron and the freely
permeable to water
segments. Of course,
it's pulling water in to
the lumen because by
the osmotic gradient.
So it increases urine
volume, and that's going to
promote diuresis. It
increases urinary excretion of
whatever solutes get dried
along with it, and it will
expand the extracellular
fluid. So it distributes in the
ECF, and that's going to
extract water from cells.
What do we use it
for? To reduce the
intracranial pressure
with edema or
intraocular pressure,
one or the other.
It's an adjunct
in some cisplatin
regimens to induce
forced diuresis.
Forced diuresis is usually
just done with sodium
chloride solution, isotonic
sodium chloride solution
mannitol has been
traditionally used it's less so
recently because of the lack
of clear evidence for the
benefit of the use so
increasing osmotic pressure
in the plasma causes water
to shift out of the brain
current parenchyma or the
eye tissue or and the eye
tissue actually and
then all that water gets
transported to the kidneys
and is excreted as urine can
it cause well volume
expansion of course and it can
cause headache dizziness
nausea vomiting heart
failure complication that's
with this pulmonary edema
because they're in heart
failure patients they're
already they already have
edema and the heart is
not pumping as well as
it normally would and so
the fluid has a tendency
to get backed up and heart
failure patients just
cannot manage all of this
extra fluid coming in
because of mannitol presence.
So fluorid pulmonary
edema as the fluid
overwhelms the heart's
ability to pump it out.
Hyponatremia in patients
with severe renal
impairment, the mannitol
cannot be excreted, The
plasma volume increases,
and as a result,
everything in there gets
diluted, so hyponatremia.
Dehydration and electrolyte
imbalance with all
of this extra osmotic
fluid flowing through
the kidneys can cause
rapid diuresis with loss
of electrolytes,
dehydration, hypovolemia,
hypernatremia,
hyperkalemia, and so on.
Nephrotoxicity. It
can cause acute kidney
injury in patients who
are already at risk.
Also, what do you
have to do? Monitor
carefully. And it
should be used by
people who are
experienced with its use.
Contraindications, of
course, allergy to it.
Severe dehydration.
Severe renal disease.
Renal dysfunction after
mannitol administration.
Active cranial bleed, with
the exception of a craniotomy.
Progressive heart
failure. Anybody who's
already got pulmonary
edema and congestion.
And that's basically it
with the osmotic diuretics.
Pretty simple concepts.
And here are the
questions and answers.
Questions and answers.
and a little case vignette
and a summary which I'll go
over the summary along with
the going over all of
those review questions and
the optional separate video
if you wish to watch it.
So that concludes part two that
concludes the diuretic
agents lecture.